<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: opinion | Craig Aspinall]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.craigaspinall.com/blog/categories/opinion/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.craigaspinall.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-06-15T07:05:44+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.craigaspinall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Craig Aspinall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quitting Facebook]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigaspinall.com/blog/2011/04/24/quitting-facebook/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-24T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigaspinall.com/blog/2011/04/24/quitting-facebook</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After listening to Mark Pesce's controversial keynote presentation at LinuxConf Australia 2011 (and giving myself a couple of months to think about it), I've decided that the time has come to leave Facebook, and to encourage others to do the same. If you want to understand why, I strongly recommend you read "Mark's presentation":http://blog.futurestreetconsulting.com/2011/01/28/smoke-signals/ but here are the reasons in a nutshell.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>The most valuable piece of information about you is your social graph and the communication that occurs across that graph. That reveals more about you, your personal interests, even your secrets, than anything else that you do online. And Facebook is watching and recording it all.</p>

<p>This might not be so disturbing if Facebook had not repeatedly let members down with regards to the privacy of their data. Or if people actually understood what information they are divulging to Facebook. Whilst many have pointed to the likes of Microsoft and Google as potential dystopian "big brother" overlords, Facebook is probably much better poised in reality.</p>

<p>So I'm making my own (sadly insignificant) stand by quitting. I encourage you to do the same.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The great thing about standards...]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigaspinall.com/blog/2010/11/22/the-great-thing-about-standards/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-22T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigaspinall.com/blog/2010/11/22/the-great-thing-about-standards</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>… is that there's so many of them to choose from. They're like Java frameworks, everyone has got one! I guess it's down to control. People don't want to invest in something that they don't have control over, so they create another standard, manage to get it ratified by some standards body, and then claim that they are standards compliant. But if we're not all using the same standard, how much value does the standard have?</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I've spent a considerable amount of time this weekend creating alternative versions of the "Coding By Numbers":http://www.codingbynumbers.com/ podcast. We have been using the "AAC":http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Advanced_Audio_Coding format since it gives you the best bang for your buck in terms of quality versus size, but we've had a bunch of feedback asking for an "MP3":http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MP3 version because not all media players support AAC.</p>

<p>A few weeks ago, my co-host "Steve":http://dalts.net/ was fortunate enough to meet with "Richard Stallman":http://stallman.org/ from the "Free Software Foundation":http://www.fsf.org/, who won't listen to any digital audio unless it is recorded in an open format such as "Ogg Vorbis":http://www.vorbis.com/. In fact he thinks we shouldn't be offering anything but open formats and he's probably right, but if people are having problems with AAC support, can you imagine the problems people would have if we only offered Ogg Vorbis?</p>

<p>So there's three standards that we now offer for the podcast, but those aren't the only standards we could choose from. There's also "FLAC":http://flac.sourceforge.net/, "MP2":http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MP2, "WAV":http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WAV, "WMA":http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windows_Media_Audio and that's before we even start on the voice specific codecs we could use! And there's so little real difference between them that you have to question why they all exist. Perhaps standards would be better controlled by a benevolent dictator than committees?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dead trees are dead to me]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigaspinall.com/blog/2010/11/19/dead-trees-are-dead-to-me/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-19T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigaspinall.com/blog/2010/11/19/dead-trees-are-dead-to-me</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I haven't bought a dead tree version of a book for years. If it's not available as either an ebook or an audiobook then I don't buy it. The same goes for music, and when the film industry realises that DRM is a fallacy, I'll be able to do the same with video too.</p>

<p>Ideally I want to have my entire collection of books with me wherever I go, but not just books. I want to take my music and video collection too. The iPhone kickstarted a revolution in convergence devices that go a long way towards making this possible. Whilst I can't carry my entire music and video collection on my phone because they are too large, I can carry my favourites and still have enough space for all my ebooks.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Recently I've encountered a couple of situations where my phone doesn't suffice though. I write a lot of notes on paper (or 3x5 index cards) and they are prone to getting lost or recycled accidentally. For this the phone keyboard is too small, and I'm not sure whether I would be more comfortable with a pen or stylus over a keyboard anyway. I also started playing the guitar again and printing guitar tab is a waste of paper and often difficult to read. Again the phone is too small to display this type of content effectively.</p>

<p>I thought about getting an eReader like the Kindle or Nook to address this issue, but I'm not convinced they will provide everything I need. I think they would be fantastic for replacing paper content, but I'm not so sure about the note taking, even though the Kindle has a physical keyboard and the Nook has a virtual keyboard that would fill an iPhone screen.</p>

<p>The elephant in the room is the iPad. It can do everything my phone can do but has a bigger screen. The battery life isn't as good as an eReader and the screen will get full of fingerprints, but it will do everything I want. When it came out, I said I couldn't see a need for one in my life because it didn't solve any problems for me. Then I chuckled to myself as I saw lots of people buy them, play with them for two weeks and then struggle to figure out what they were going to use it for! Now I do have a use for a 10” iPhone I feel like a bit of a dummy. I hate it when Apple are right!</p>

<p>Even so, given my feelings towards Apple right now though, I am loathed to give them more of my hard earned cash. The only semi-viable alternative I have found is the Archos 10 internet tablet. There are plenty of cheap Chinese rip offs of the iPad, but I've used Archos devices before and they were very good quality. Physically and technically it has very similar specifications to the iPad but it runs the Android 2.2 Froyo operating system. Given that Android phones have similar capabilities to an iPhone, I figure an Android tablet must have similar capabilities to an iPad!</p>

<p>Only time (and finances) will tell whether I end up with an eReader, an iPad or another tablet device, but I wouldn't be surprised if one of them turned to be my next gadget purchase, so I can remove more dead trees from my life!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What's the value of free?]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigaspinall.com/blog/2010/11/16/whats-the-value-of-free/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-16T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigaspinall.com/blog/2010/11/16/whats-the-value-of-free</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was looking something up on "Wikipedia":http://www.wikipedia.org/ when I saw this "banner":http://wikimediafoundation.org/w/index.php?title=WMFJA1/AU containing an appeal from Jimmy Wales for donations to the WikiMedia Foundation. It made me question how much we take services like Wikipedia for granted? If you decide that you should donate, how much would you give? How do you but a value on a free service?</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I have no problem discerning the value proposition with the '"Freemium":http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freemium' services like "LastPass":http://www.lastpass.com, where the "extra" value I get from my $1/month are listed in bullet points before I hand over my money. However in this case you don't get any "extra" value in exchange for your cash. There is the possibility of less value being delivered if you don't make a donation, but that's not a certainty either.</p>

<p>So how much should you donate? Perhaps it should be the cost of a reasonable "dead tree" encyclopaedia? On the other hand if every user gives a nominal $1 donation, it would raise $400,000,000, which I think would see them through for a while!</p>

<p>Of course, just like free and open source software, there is more than one way to contribute. You could also contribute with your time, by adding, editing or reviewing articles.</p>

<p>I decided that I'd like Wikipedia to stick around, so I'll make a small donation and start contributing where I can. If you use it, what will you do?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Oracle, the best thing to happen to OpenJDK?]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigaspinall.com/blog/2010/11/14/oracle-the-best-thing-for-openjdk/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-14T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigaspinall.com/blog/2010/11/14/oracle-the-best-thing-for-openjdk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I can't believe I am writing this, but could Oracle be the best thing to happen to OpenJDK? I know that writing 30 posts in 30 days is driving me a little crazy, but have I really lost that many marbles before the halfway point? Just how can the company that is being "sued by the US government":http://www.businessweek.com/news/2010-07-29/oracle-sued-by-u-s-in-case-claiming-overcharges.html for their alleged dishonesty be doing good things with such an indispensable open source project?</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Well, despite my many misgivings about the "delays":http://blogs.oracle.com/javaone/2010/09/plan_b_wins.html to all the interesting content in JDK7, their willingness to take the flak and do what is necessary to steady the ship shows they have the guts to make tough decisions. Sun kept promising but never really delivered. If Oracle start delivering regularly then I'll be less critical of the additional delays to JDK7.</p>

<p>They've also persuaded "IBM":http://www-03.ibm.com/press/us/en/pressrelease/32708.wss and "Apple":http://www.apple.com/pr/library/2010/11/12openjdk.html to join the OpenJDK effort, something which Sun never managed to do. This brings all the major JDK vendors together in one place and hopefully we will see the best features of each of the JDK implementations (IBM, Oracle/BEA, Oracle/Sun and Apple) being merged into the open source offering.</p>

<p>The only question that still nags in the back of my mind is their motive. Whilst it all seems rosy on the surface, persuading IBM to back OpenJDK instead of Apache Harmony could have an ulterior motive. Oracle are attempting to "sue Google":http://www.reuters.com/article/idUSTRE67B5G720100813 over the use of Java in Android, and which class libraries do you suppose Android uses? You guessed it, Apache Harmony's! By getting IBM to switch to OpenJDK, it further isolates Google.</p>

<p>I'm not quite ready to believe that is a co-incidence yet!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
