<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: coding by numbers | Craig Aspinall]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.craigaspinall.com/blog/categories/coding-by-numbers/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.craigaspinall.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-06-17T06:19:26+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.craigaspinall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Craig Aspinall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What is functional programming?]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigaspinall.com/blog/2011/06/23/what-is-functional-programming/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-23T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigaspinall.com/blog/2011/06/23/what-is-functional-programming</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I gave a talk at our "Coding By Numbers meetup":http://www.meetup.com/CodingByNumbers/events/21665201 tonight that attempts to peel away some of the mystery surrounding that question. It was a small audience but they appeared to appreciate it and I hope I was able to show them that many of the benefits of functional programming are easily accessible.</p>

<p>I originally put this presentation together for a functional programming group that I started at work, for those that are interested in learning more about functional programming and ultimately applying it to their day jobs.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>The focus of the presentation is really about getting to the crux of what functional programming is, and away from all the FUD(Fear Uncertainty and Doubt) that surrounds it. It also presents a simple example in Java, refactoring a "naive" solution into one that is more readable, testable and maintainable, by applying functional programming principles. The presentation finishes off with an example solution to the same problem in Haskell.</p>

<p>The "handout":talks/what-is-fp/handout.pdf contains the slides with all of my reader notes, which is essentially a transcript of the presentation.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The great thing about standards...]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigaspinall.com/blog/2010/11/22/the-great-thing-about-standards/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-22T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigaspinall.com/blog/2010/11/22/the-great-thing-about-standards</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>… is that there's so many of them to choose from. They're like Java frameworks, everyone has got one! I guess it's down to control. People don't want to invest in something that they don't have control over, so they create another standard, manage to get it ratified by some standards body, and then claim that they are standards compliant. But if we're not all using the same standard, how much value does the standard have?</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I've spent a considerable amount of time this weekend creating alternative versions of the "Coding By Numbers":http://www.codingbynumbers.com/ podcast. We have been using the "AAC":http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Advanced_Audio_Coding format since it gives you the best bang for your buck in terms of quality versus size, but we've had a bunch of feedback asking for an "MP3":http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MP3 version because not all media players support AAC.</p>

<p>A few weeks ago, my co-host "Steve":http://dalts.net/ was fortunate enough to meet with "Richard Stallman":http://stallman.org/ from the "Free Software Foundation":http://www.fsf.org/, who won't listen to any digital audio unless it is recorded in an open format such as "Ogg Vorbis":http://www.vorbis.com/. In fact he thinks we shouldn't be offering anything but open formats and he's probably right, but if people are having problems with AAC support, can you imagine the problems people would have if we only offered Ogg Vorbis?</p>

<p>So there's three standards that we now offer for the podcast, but those aren't the only standards we could choose from. There's also "FLAC":http://flac.sourceforge.net/, "MP2":http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MP2, "WAV":http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WAV, "WMA":http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windows_Media_Audio and that's before we even start on the voice specific codecs we could use! And there's so little real difference between them that you have to question why they all exist. Perhaps standards would be better controlled by a benevolent dictator than committees?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
