<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: conferences | Craig Aspinall]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.craigaspinall.com/blog/categories/conferences/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.craigaspinall.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-06-17T06:19:26+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.craigaspinall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Craig Aspinall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Uberconf, Uber Geeks, Uber Tired!]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigaspinall.com/blog/2011/07/15/uberconf/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-15T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigaspinall.com/blog/2011/07/15/uberconf</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My first "Uberconf":http://uberconf.com is over. Was it worth the 16,000 mile (26,000km) round trip and a week away from my family? It was definitely worth making the trip but now I need a holiday to get over it because I'm exhausted. Next time, I'll bring my family along for the ride and have a vacation afterwards!</p>

<p>The conference is a learning and networking feast, with a wide variety of great content delivered professionally by awesome speakers that really understand their subject matter. The Westin Westiminster hotel was also a great venue that catered well for a conference of this size, in terms of the rooms, the delegate accommodation and the food.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Almost all of the sessions I went to were good, but if I had to pick my top three sessions it would be these:</p>

<p>h5. <em>Encryption on the JVM: Boot Camp</em> by "Matthew Mccullough":http://twitter.com/#!/matthewmccull</p>

<p>Matthew completely blew me away with this talk. Not because of the subject matter but <em>how</em> he delivered it. I have never seen anyone deliver a presentation as professionally as Matthew did. I attended two of his other talks and he was just as good in both of those, even when the wifi was conspiring against him! He is definitely the Steve Jobs of the No Fluff Just Stuff crowd!</p>

<p>This is a subject that I knew next to nothing about before the session and I left feeling confident that I could go and implement encryption correctly and effectively afterwards. I also really enjoyed his <em>Thinking in Git</em> presentation which gave me lots more reasons to love Git!</p>

<p>I also got the chance to sit next to Matthew for dinner one evening and he is a really nice guy too. Very engaging, humble and friendly. A definite star in our industry.</p>

<p>h5. <em>Complexity Theory in Software Development</em> by "Tim Berglund":http://twitter.com/#!/tlberglund</p>

<p>Like Matthew, Tim is an excellent presenter and this talk was probably the most thought provoking of all those I attended. It was a whistlestop tour of what <em>complexity theory</em> is and what bearing is has on our daily lives and the software we write. It was both educational and challenging in exactly the right proportions.</p>

<p>He also delivered a wonderful skit after dinner one evening, called "Oh, The Methods You'll Compose":http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xZKmmdCnTUY, which almost got a standing ovation from the audience! It reminded me very much of Guy Steele's and Richard Gabriel's "50 in 50":http://blip.tv/file/1472720/ keynote that I was fortunate enough to see live at "YOW!":http://yowaustralia.com.au/ Brisbane last year.</p>

<p>h5. <em>Towards a Humane Interface</em> by "Venkat Subramaniam":http://twitter.com/#!/venkat_s</p>

<p>I wasn't able to make any of Venkat's other talks but I had been told that he was an excellent speaker and didn't want to miss out on the opportunity to see him. This subject wouldn't have been top of my list of his talks, but it was the only one where I didn't have a clash!</p>

<p>As it happened it was the last session of the conference and Venkat was in excellent form! He engaged the audience with some great anecdotes and was animated and jovial throughout. He clearly has a passion for all the work that he does and it was a great privilege to see him in action.</p>

<p>Narrowing it down to three talks was very difficult and the three I've picked out are the ones I enjoyed the most, but these guys also deserve special mention:</p>

<h1>"Neal Ford":http://twitter.com/#!/neal4d for <em>Build Your Own Technology Radar</em>, which was another very thought provoking session.</h1>

<h1>"Frank Kim":http://twitter.com/#!/sansappsec for <em>Tricks of the Trade: What Every Developer Should Know About Application Security</em>, which was both educational and very scary as we worked through case studies of actual security breaches and Frank demo'd how easy some of the common hacks are!</h1>

<h1>"Hamlet D'Arcy":http://twitter.com/#!/HamletDRC for <em>Effective Groovy</em> which was my first Uberconf session and had some great lessons for intermediate Groovy developers such as myself to learn and improve from.</h1>

<p>Last but not least I need to say thank you to "Jay Zimmerman":http://twitter.com/#!/nofluff, Mr. No Fluff himself. I know that he was very helpful in getting me to the conference and he made a point of coming over and checking how I was getting on, obviously remembering the e-mail exchange he had with my team leader. Now I know that is just typical of his attention to detail and the reason that the No Fluff Just Stuff conferences have the reputation that they do.</p>

<p>The only criticisms I had from the conference (and I know other attendees had the same problems) were:</p>

<h1>There were 10 tracks and in many slots I wanted to attend five talks. Having too much good content is clearly an excellent problem to have, but I really feel like I missed out on more than I got (which was still a lot).</h1>

<h1>The multi session workshops meant you had the choice of missing out on 1-4 sessions at a time, or not attending the workshop.</h1>

<p>Clearly the conference couldn't be any longer, neither the speakers or the delegates would survive! Maybe grouping the sessions so that all the beginner/introductory sessions ran concurrently, then the intermediate then the expert ones. Given everyone will be at different levels on different tracks, they could have the choice of going from beginner to expert in one track, or cut between them depending on their existing expertise level. Also grouping the workshops together might work better.</p>

<p>Finally, I met a lot of very talented, very passionate and very friendly people at this conference, delegates and speakers alike. I cannot recommend it highly enough.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flash - friend or foe?]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigaspinall.com/blog/2010/03/12/flash-friend-or-foe/"/>
    <updated>2010-03-12T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigaspinall.com/blog/2010/03/12/flash-friend-or-foe</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I attended "Barcamp Gold Coast IV":http://www.meetup.com/barcampqld/ last weekend which was an awesome experience despite the low turn out. The lack of attendance did prompt me to host a couple of impromptu sessions though, one being a rehash of a blog post I wrote last year about RIA technologies and where I thought it was all heading.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>The most interesting thing was that I conducted a quick straw poll at the start of the session to gauge feeling towards Flash, with surprising results. There were a mix of people in the audience, from accountants to developers, and <em>every single one of them</em> hated Flash! Some because of it's use in advertising, some because it hogs resources on their system, but nobody wanted it on their system and some people were actively blocking Flash content from their browsers.</p>

<p>Now I'm no fan of Flash but I was not expected such a landslide result! Given that I already thought Flash was under threat from HTML 5, this lack of consumer enthusiasm for it has to be another nail in the coffin.</p>

<p>Since my last blog post, Google has also been successful in it's acquisition of On2, the company from whom the Flash video codec is licensed. Google can now do what they want with that codec, such as open source it or freely license it to other browser vendors, subject to any contractual obligations On2 have with Adobe and Oracle (who license the same codec for JavaFX). Is that the sound of another nail being readied?</p>

<p>All told I think the developments of the last few months have been positive ones for internet consumers, since it should start to resolve some of the sticky issues with the HTML 5 specification process. But I think it is more bad news for Adobe who, sooner or later, are going to have to stop shoving the Flash runtime down people's throats.</p>

<p>The only runtime people seem to want in their browsers now is the JavaScript runtime and between "Google":http://code.google.com/p/v8/, "Apple":http://www.apple.com/safari/whats-new.html#performance and "Mozilla":https://wiki.mozilla.org/JavaScript:TraceMonkey, we have three great implementations competing against each other. If the HTML 5 committee can reach an agreement on which video format the @<video>@ tag must support, then I don't see any reason left for any content provider to use Flash (or "Silverlight":http://www.silverlight.net/ or "JavaFX":http://www.javafx.com/) at all.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
