<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: linux | Craig Aspinall]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.craigaspinall.com/blog/categories/linux/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.craigaspinall.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-06-15T07:05:44+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.craigaspinall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Craig Aspinall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mmmmm... Minty Macbook!]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigaspinall.com/blog/2010/11/13/minty-macbook/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-13T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigaspinall.com/blog/2010/11/13/minty-macbook</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I started on my current project and got a new developer workstation, I took advantage of an official "Ubuntu":http://www.ubuntu.com/ distribution sanctioned for use within the company. Apart from a few wrinkles with the authentication against the Windows domains, it has been a real pleasure to use, so when I rebuilt my MacBook recently, I decided that I would use "Bootcamp":http://www.apple.com/support/bootcamp/ and tri-boot it (Max OS X, Windows 7 and Linux).</p>

<p>I started out with the regular Ubuntu distribution, but it didn't seem to work all that well. It certainly wasn't a slick as it is on my workstation at work. I was having problems with the trackpad and the wifi adapter in particular. Then someone recommended "Linux Mint":http://www.linuxmint.com/, so I scrapped Ubuntu and installed that instead.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>It installed straight away and everything aside from the iSight camera worked immediately. It can access the OS X and Windows 7 partitions and even the MP4 video and MP3 audio codecs were installed so I could play back my media from my iTunes library.</p>

<p>On top of that, it performs snappily and it still has the excellent package management of Ubuntu. I was even more pleasantly surprised when it paired with my iPhone and connected to the internet on the first attempt!</p>

<p>So if you've been thinking about giving Linux a whirl, then Linux Mint is a really good, low fuss candidate.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
